Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Communist and Socialist Serials TAM.747
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Communist and Socialist Serials
1850-2013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communist Party of the United States of America
Revolutionary Communist Party, USA
Progressive Labor Party
Socialist Workers Party
New American Movement (Organization)
Labour Party (Great Britain)
TAM.747
94 Linear Feet in 135 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, 120 flat boxes, a folder in a shared manuscript box, and a folder in a shared oversized flat box.
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Communist and Socialist Serials collects 1,945 serials and publications chronicling the activity of national and international Communist and Socialist groups, published between 1850 and 2013, originally received by the Tamiment Library through subscriptions, donations, and as part of archival collections. The majority of the collection consists of incomplete runs of newsletters, newspapers, reports, information bulletins, theoretical journals, and informally prepared communiqués issued by political groups. The serials document the rise and fall of Communism and Socialism at a granular level, rich in detailed first-person accounts of key political events: World War II, the Vietnam conflict, German reunification. Publications originate from national political parties, smaller splinter groups and factions, current affairs magazines, and unions and labor coalitions at the local and national level. The collection contains hundreds of titles documenting Communism and Socialism internationally, in serials and reports emanating from established national political organizations, as well as material documenting political activity in Puerto Rico, Canada, South Africa, and elsewhere. No complete runs of publications are contained herein, and in most cases only a handful of issues of each publication are held.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection combines serials relating to the labor movement drawn from two discrete groups of material held by the Tamiment Library. The first was a partially inventoried backlog of serials, received by the library through donations, subscriptions, and in archival collections. The second group consisted of around 1,700 serials, newspapers, and magazines, organized by title as an artificial collection, referred to as Periodicals.001 or Boxed Newspapers. This material was combined, inventoried, and arranged and described in subject-based categories in 2017. The accession number related to this collection is 2017.049.
In September 2024, five issues of Catalyst: A Socialist Journal of the Social Services and one issue of the Party Builder Bulletin was transferred from the Ruth Wilson Collection of Human Rights and Social Work Records (TAM 342). The accession number associated with this accretion is 2024.045.
Existence and Location of Copies
In some instances researchers may be required to consult microfilm copies of material held in this collection. Information on microfilm copies is included below each title listing.
Arrangement
This collection imposes an artificial arrangement on a range of disparate material separated from the order in which it was originally received at Tamiment Library. The material is separated into two, dividing serials into groups of similar material based on place of publication. The first series, Series I: American Publications, collects serials issued in the United States. The second series, Series II: International Publications, divides serials into two subseries: Subseries II.A consists of broadly-termed 'Soviet' publications, predominantly published in Russia; and Subseries II.B collects the remaining international titles. Within each series, material is arranged at the file level, in alphabetical order by publishing organization. Where possible issues of each publication are organized chronologically, grouped by year. Each title is listed alongside its publishing organization, and city of origin, where this information is available.
Scope and Contents
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Collection of Communist and Socialist Serials collects 1,945 serials and publications chronicling the activity of national and international Communist and Socialist groups, published between 1850 and 2013, originally received by the Tamiment Library through subscriptions, donations, and as part of archival collections.
The majority of the collection consists of incomplete runs of newsletters, newspapers, reports, information bulletins, theoretical journals, and informally prepared communiqués. The serials document the trajectories of Communism and Socialism at a granular level, rich in detailed first-person accounts of political events, variously occurring against the backdrop of World War II, the Cold War, the Vietnam war, and the fall of the Soviet Union. Serials provide a detailed accounting and lively discussion of the ideological evolution and division of Communism and Socialism, providing commentary on contemporary news - the trial of the Rosenbergs, McCarthyism, the Vietnam conflict, the reunification of Germany - and ranging in scale from pictorial accounts of community activism undertaken by various subgroups of Students for a Democratic Society to typewritten tracts responding to the death of Mao Zedong. One-off and irregularly published small-run pamphlets and bulletins circulate news, opinion, polemics, rebuttals, manifestos, disquisitions, and propaganda. Among the topics covered are anti-fascist efforts, labor negotiations, black liberation movements, the formation of solidarities between political constituencies, tensions and fissures in local and national groups, the "red scares" of the 20th century, and anti-Semitism in the United States.
Publications originate from national political parties, smaller splinter groups and factions, current affairs magazines, unions and labor coalitions at the local and national level, and publishing houses distributing essays explicating political policies and philosophies. Among the organizations well represented in the collection are the Communist Party of the USA; the Revolutionary Communist Party; the Progressive Labor Party; the Socialist Workers Party; the Revolutionary Socialist League; New American Movement; the British Labour party; as well as numerous reports and essays issued by Pioneer Publishers; New Century Publishers; Foreign Languages Press; and Getting Together Publications. Among the titles held in significant volume are the Bulletin, published by the Workers League; Burning Spear, published by the African People's Socialist Party; the Revolutionary Socialist League's Torch; the Party for Workers Power's Spark; the Revolutionary Communist Party's Revolution; The Militant; Unity; and variants of Quatrieme Internationale.
In addition to American publications, there are also hundreds of titles documenting Communism and Socialism abroad, in serials and reports emanating from large, established governmental and independent organizations - China's Foreign Languages Press; Russia's Novosti Press Agency; and Britain's Fabian Society, among others - as well as accumulations of material describing political activity in Puerto Rico, Canada, Jamaica, South Africa, and elsewhere. No complete runs of publications are contained herein, and in most cases only a handful of issues of each publication are held.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of certain original materials, researchers may be required to consult microfilm copies, preservation photocopies, or digital images of material in this collection.
Labor movement -- United States -- History; Socialism -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Communism -- United States -- History -- 20th century.; Socialism -- United States -- Periodicals.; Communism -- Periodicals.; Political parties -- United States -- History -- 20th century.
- Series I: American Publications, 1881-2010; 68.4 Linear Feet in 89 manuscript boxes, 2 half manuscript boxes, and 102 flat boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series collects 1,260 publications -- serials, journals, magazines, newsletters, bulletins, pamphlets, and reports -- issued by a variety of local and national parties, organizations, political organizers, commentators, and affiliated interest groups in the United States. The majority of the series collects regularly published bulletins, newsletters, and newspapers, circulating news and discussion within communities of Communist Party members and activists. One-off reports and occasional papers address a variety of topics in detail, including working regulations, meetings and conventions, and Communist and Socialist movements abroad. Well represented serials in this collection include Burning Spear, Freedom Socialist, The Militant, Socialist Workers Party's Bulletin, and the Central Committee of the Workers League's Bulletin, alongside various titles dedicated to social justice issues intersecting with communist and socialist thought, among them the Gay Socialist Newsletter, Asians in Struggle, and publications dedicated to groups affiliated with the Democratic Socialists of America (including DSA Green News, Socialist Perspectives on Race, and the Democratic Socialists of America Feminist Commission's Not Far Enough).
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by publishing organization name.
  - International Discussion Bulletin: 14th World Congress, 1995; cuid11443 (Box 94, Folder 12)
  - Across Frontiers: Across Frontiers, Berkeley, CA, 1985-1989 (Box 203, Folder 7-8)
  - Workers' Action: Action, New York, NY, 1977-1990; cuid13370 (Box 67, Folder 5-6)
  - Ad Hoc Bulletin: Ad Hoc Committee for a Marxist-Leninist Party, USA, New York, NY, 1972; cuid11444 (Box 94, Folder 13)
  - Socialist Development in Africa: Africa Research Group, Cambridge, MA, 1969-1970; cuid11445 (Box 94, Folder 14)
  - Burning Spear: African People's Socialist Party, Oakland, CA, circa 1960s; cuid11446 (Box 48, Folder 1-6, Box 49, Box 50, Folder 1-5, Box 51, Box 52, Folder 1-7, Box 41, Folder 7)
  - Newsletter: afro-americans for halstead and boutelle, 1968; cuid11447 (Box 94, Folder 15)
  - Documents from Latin American Communist Parties: Afro-Asian Latin American Peoples' Solidarity Forum, Seattle, WA, 1976; cuid11448 (Box 94, Folder 16)
  - Alliance: AFS, Mission Hills, CA, 1992; cuid11449 (Box 94, Folder 17)
  - Freedom: Albert R. Parsons Assembly, Chicago, IL, 1891; cuid11450 (Box 152, Folder 8)
  - Chess News from Russia: Albrecht Buschke, New York, NY, 1945; cuid11451 (Box 94, Folder 18)
  - Hiss Family Correspondence: Alger Hiss, 1952; cuid11452 (Box 79, Folder 17)
  - New Counterattack: American Business Consultants, Inc., New York, NY, 1955; cuid11453 (Box 94, Folder 19)
  - Rape of the First Amendment: American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born, New York, NY, 1900; cuid11454 (Box 94, Folder 20)
  - American Communist: American Communist Movement, Oakland, CA, 1970; cuid11455 (Box 121, Folder 9)
  - People's America Daily News: American Communist Workers Movement (Marxist-Leninist), Cleveland, OH, 1970-1971; cuid11456 (Box 123, Folder 1)
  - American Forum For Socialist Education: American Forum, New York, NY, 1957; cuid11457 (Box 94, Folder 21)
  - AIM: American Independent Movement, New Haven, CT, 1979-1980; cuid11458 (Box 85, Folder 1)
  - AIM: The Bulletin of the American Independent Movement: American Independent Movement, New Haven, CT, 1968; cuid11459 (Box 85, Folder 2)
  - AIMS Occasional Paper: American Institute For Marxist Studies, New York, NY, 1965-1968, 1972-1979, 1982; cuid11460 (Box 82, Folder 17-18, Box 85, Folder 3-8, Box 227, Folder 8)
  - Bibliographical Series: American Institute for Marxist Studies, New York, NY, 1965-1972, 1975, 1979, 1983; cuid11461 (Box 100, Folder 1-3)
  - Christianity in the Soviet Union: American Institute for Marxist Studies, New York, NY, 1972; cuid11462 (Box 94, Folder 22)
  - Marxism and Psychology: A Bibliography: American Institute for Marxist Studies, New York, NY, 1980; cuid11463 (Box 161, Folder 24)
  - Occasional Paper: American Institute for Marxist Studies, New York, NY, 1983; cuid11464 (Box 94, Folder 24)
  - Occasional Paper: American Institute for Marxist Studies, New York, NY, 1977; cuid11465 (Box 94, Folder 23)
  - Occasional Papers: American Institute for Marxist Studies, New York, NY, 1965, 1975, 1978; cuid11466 (Box 94, Folder 25)
  - Paul Robeson Rediscovered: American Institute for Marxist Studies, 1976; cuid11467 (Box 99, Folder 1)
  - Youth Against War and Fascism: American League Against War and Fascism, circa 1930s; cuid11468 (Box 99, Folder 2)
  - Soviet Culture in Wartime: American Russian Institute, San Francisco, CA, 1942-1943; cuid11469 (Box 99, Folder 3)
  - VM Molotov speech: American Russian Institute, San Francisco, CA, 1945; cuid11470 (Box 99, Folder 4)
  - Soviet Health Care in Peace and War: American Russian Institute for Cultural Relations with the Soviet Union, Inc., New York, NY, 1943; cuid11471 (Box 99, Folder 5)
  - Marxist Vanguard: American Workers' Communist Party, New York, NY, 1972-1973; cuid11472 (Box 123, Folder 2)
  - Movement: American Worker's Party, New York, NY, 1985-1988; cuid11473 (Box 123, Folder 6)
  - Our Struggle: Anti Racism, Latino, African American Commissions DSA, Sacramento, CA, 1993; cuid11474 (Box 99, Folder 8)
  - Anti-Colonial Bulletin: Anti-Colonial Committee of the Independent Socialist Union, 1966; cuid11475 (Box 99, Folder 9)
  - News Bulletin: Architects' Committee, National Council of American-Soviet Friendship, Inc., New York, NY, 1944; cuid11476 (Box 99, Folder 10, Box 232, Folder 9)
  - Arise: Arise, New York, NY, 1935; cuid11477 (Box 99, Folder 11)
  - Rank and File Bulletin: Arizona Left Review, Tuscon, AZ, 1973; cuid11478 (Box 99, Folder 12)
  - Solidarity Atlanta: Atlanta Democratic Socialists of America, Atlanta, GA, 1990; cuid11479 (Box 99, Folder 13)
  - Fight Back!: Attica Brigade, Staten Island, NY, 1973-1974; cuid11480 (Box 90, Folder 3)
  - Stony Brook Attica Brigade Newsletter: Attica Brigade, Stony Brook, NY, 1973; cuid11481 (Box 99, Folder 14, Box 130, Folder 9)
  - Revolutionary Cause: August Twenty-Ninth Movement (ML), Los Angeles, CA, 1976-1978; cuid11482 (Box 57, Folder 8-9, Box 213, Folder 8)
  - GM Van Nuys Worker: Auto Club of the Communist Party, USA, Los Angeles, CA, 1985-1986; cuid11483 (Box 99, Folder 15)
  - DSA Today: Baltimore Democratic Socialists of America, Baltimore, MD, 1989, 1994; cuid11484 (Box 99, Folder 16)
  - A Century of World Communism: A Selective Chronological Outline: Barron's Educational Series, Inc., Woodbury, NY, 1970; cuid11485 (Box 99, Folder 17)
  - Cultural Revolution in China: Bay Area Radical Education Project, San Francisco, CA, 1967; cuid11486 (Box 99, Folder 18)
  - Bay Area Worker = El Obrero de la area de la bahia: Bay Area Worker, San Francisco, CA, 1972; cuid11487 (Box 123, Folder 3, Box 207, Folder 1)
  - Mao as a Dialectician: Bewick/ED, Detroit, MI, 1971; cuid11488 (Box 99, Folder 19)
  - Toward Socialism: Bill Haywood Communist Club of Illegally Expelled Members of CPUSA, New York, NY, 1949; cuid11489 (Box 99, Folder 20)
  - Black Revolutionary: Black Revolutionary Party, USA, Detroit, MI, 1971; cuid11490 (Box 123, Folder 4)
  - Communist = El Comunista: Black Workers Congress, Detroit, MI, 1974-1975; cuid11491 (Box 123, Folder 7)
  - The Struggle against revisionism and opportunism: Black Workers Congress, Detroit, MI, 1974; cuid11492 (Box 99, Folder 21)
  - Cambridge Project - Social Science for Social Control: Bob Park, Cambridge, MA, 1969; cuid11493 (Box 104, Folder 5)
  - Chispa: Bolshevik-Leninists of Puerto Rico, San Juan, Puerto Rico, 1937; cuid11494 (Box 99, Folder 22)
  - 1917: Journal of the International Bolshevik Tendency: Bolshevik Tendency, Oakland, CA/Toronto, Canada, 1992-1995 (Box 203, Folder 1-2)
  - The Great Conspiracy Against Russia: Boni & Gaer, Inc. Publishers, New York, NY, 1946; cuid11495 (Box 99, Folder 23)
  - Newsletter: Boston Area Chapter New American Movement, Boston, MA, 1980; cuid11496 (Box 99, Folder 24)
  - History of the Second World War: BPC Publishing Ltd., Hicksville, NY, 1974; cuid11497 (Box 99, Folder 25)
  - Heresy: Bradford-Brown Educational Company, Inc., Galion, OH, 1924; cuid11498 (Box 161, Folder 25)
  - Brecht Forum: Brecht Forum, New York, NY, 2004; cuid11499 (Box 99, Folder 26)
  - Brecht Forum: Brecht Forum, New York, NY, 1999-2000, 2004; cuid11500 (Box 123, Folder 10)
  - Mascot: Brewster Rolls Royce Nucleus of the Workers (Communist) Party of America, Long Island City, Long Island City, NY, 1928; cuid11501 (Box 100, Folder 4)
  - Internal Bulletin: British Section, International Left Opposition, 1933; cuid11502 (Box 100, Folder 5)
  - Student Worker: Brooklyn Evening College Branch of the Young Communist League, Brooklyn, NY, 1938; cuid11503 (Box 100, Folder 6)
  - Leon Trotsky on Labor Party: Bulletin Publications, New York, NY, 1968; cuid11504 (Box 100, Folder 7)
  - People's Voice: C.P.U.S.A. (M-L), Vancover, Canada, 1998; cuid11505 (Box 123, Folder 11)
  - Party Forum: California State Committee CPUSA, San Francisco, California, 1956; cuid13319 (Box 198, Folder 3)
  - Let Man Prevail - Erich Fromm: Call Association, New York, NY, 1960; cuid11506 (Box 100, Folder 8)
  - Cambridge Left: Cambridge University Socialist Club, 1954; cuid11507 (Box 100, Folder 9)
  - Poor Konrad: Carmarthen Oak Press, Berkeley, CA, 1983 (Box 241, Folder 6)
  - Cuban Family Code: Center for Cuban Studies, New York, NY, 1975; cuid11508 (Box 100, Folder 10)
  - What Happened in Chile...: Center for Cuban Studies, New York, NY, circa 1970s; cuid11509 (Box 100, Folder 11)
  - International Socialist Review: Center for Economic Research and Social Change, Chicago, IL, 1952, 2000, 2002; cuid11510 (Box 100, Folder 12)
  - Michigan Working Papers in Soviet & East European Studies: Center for Russian and East European Studies, University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, circa 1960s; cuid11511 (Box 100, Folder 13)
  - International Bulletin: Central Committee, 1981; cuid11512 (Box 100, Folder 14)
  - Rally, Comrades!: Central Committee of the Communist Labor Party of the United States of North America, Chicago, IL, 1983-1995; cuid11513 (Box 92, Folder 4-7)
  - Working People's Advocate: Central Committee of the Communist League, US, 2004; cuid11514 (Box 117, Folder 1)
  - Proletariat: Central Committee of the Marxist-Leninist Organization of the USA, San Francisco, CA, 1970; cuid11515 (Box 101, Folder 2)
  - Communist = Comunista: Central Committee of the Marxist-Leninist Party, 1970-1971; cuid11516 (Box 123, Folder 8)
  - On Building the Party of the US Working Class and the Struggle Against Dogmatism and Reformism: Speeches by Bob Avakian, Member of the Central Committee of the Revolutionary Union: Central Committee of the Revolutionary Union, 1974; cuid11517 (Box 101, Folder 3)
  - 1979 Draft Resolution: The Afro-American Struggle: Central Committee, CPUSA, cuid11518 (Box 101, Folder 4)
  - Draft for Pre Convention Discussion: Main Political Resolution: Central Committee, CPUSA, New York, NY, 1979; cuid11519 (Box 101, Folder 8)
  - Bulletin: Central Committee of the Workers League, Detroit, Michigan, 1973-1990; cuid13359 (Box 202, Folder 1-5, Box 147, Folder 1-6, Box 148, Folder 1-4, Box 149, Box 150, Folder 1-7, Box 174, Box 175, Folder 1-8, Box 176, Box 177, Box 178, Box 179, Box 180, Box 181, Box 182, Box 183, Box 184, Box 185)
  - Draft Political Resolution: Central Committee, CPUSA, New York, NY, 1987; cuid11520 (Box 101, Folder 5)
  - Draft Resolution for Pre-Convention Discussion: The Afro-American Struggle: Central Committee, CPUSA, New York, NY, 1979; cuid11521 (Box 101, Folder 6)
  - Draft Resolution on Afro-American Equality: Central Committee, CPUSA, New York, NY, 1987; cuid11522 (Box 101, Folder 7)
  - Draft Resolution on Chicano/Mexican-American Equality: Central Committee, CPUSA, New York, NY, 1987; cuid11523 (Box 101, Folder 9)
  - Draft Resolution on the Work of the Party: Central Committee, CPUSA, New York, NY, 1987; cuid11524 (Box 101, Folder 10)
  - Fightback II: Political Independence Key to Advances in '85-'86: Central Committee, CPUSA, New York, NY, 1986; cuid11525 (Box 101, Folder 12)
  - Report: Central Committee, USA, 1979-1981 (Box 233, Folder 6)
  - The People Can Save Humanity and Preserve Democracy: Central Committee, CPUSA, New York, NY, 1987; cuid11526 (Box 101, Folder 13)
  - Build the Party - Build the Clubs: Central Committee/National Council, CPUSA, New York, NY, 1985; cuid11527 (Box 101, Folder 14)
  - Newsletter: Central Indiana Democratic Socialists of America, Indianapolis, IN, circa 2000s; cuid11528 (Box 101, Folder 15)
  - Seeing Red: Central Kentucky DSA, Lexington, KY, 1984; cuid11529 (Box 101, Folder 16)
  - Workers' Daily: Central Organization of U.S. Marxist-Leninists, Boston, MA, 1973; cuid11530 (Box 161, Folder 26)
  - Leader: Central Pioneer Buro. Young Pioneers of America, New York, NY, 1931; cuid11531 (Box 101, Folder 17)
  - Cahiers du mouvement ouvrier: Centre d'Etudes et de Recherches sur les Mouvements Trotskyste et Revolutionnaires Internationaux, 1998; cuid11532 (Box 101, Folder 18)
  - Right on Time: CFC Communications Section, New York, NY, 1974; cuid11533 (Box 101, Folder 19)
  - Right on Time: The Revolutionary Worker: CFC: A Collective of Liberation Centers, New York, NY, 1973-1974; cuid11534 (Box 123, Folder 12)
  - Socialist Monthly Changes: Changes Socialist Monthly, Detroit, MI, 1981 (Box 243, Folder 5)
  - Bread & Roses: Chapel Hill Socialist Community News, Chapel Hill, NC, 1973; cuid11535 (Box 101, Folder 20)
  - Money and Money Reforms: A Marxian Interpretation: Charles H. Kerr & Company, Chicago, IL, 1947; cuid11536 (Box 101, Folder 22)
  - Industrial Socialism: Charles H. Kerr & Company, Chicago, IL, circa 1910s; cuid11537 (Box 101, Folder 21)
  - Socialist Book Bulletin: Charles H. Kerr & Company, Chicago, IL, 1910-1914; cuid11538 (Box 101, Folder 23)
  - RSL Chicago Branch Newsletter: Chicago Branch of the Revolutionary Socialist League, Chicago, IL, 1981; cuid11539 (Box 101, Folder 24)
  - Chicago Socialist News: Chicago Northside New American Movement, Chicago, IL, 1978; cuid11540 (Box 101, Folder 25)
  - Parable of the Water Tank: Chicago Workers Publications, Chicago, IL, circa 1900s; cuid11541 (Box 101, Folder 26)
  - Chicago Workers' Voice: Chicago Workers Voice, Chicago, IL, 1994-1995; cuid11542 (Box 102, Folder 1)
  - Chicago Workers' Voice Theoretical Supplement: Chicago Workers' Voice, Chicago, IL, 1994; cuid11543 (Box 102, Folder 2)
  - Chicago Workers' Voice: Theoretical Journal: Chicago Worker's Voice, Chicago, IL, 1994-1998; cuid11544 (Box 102, Folder 4-6)
  - Young Chicago Worker: Chicago Unit of American Revolutionary Youth, Chicago, IL, 1972 (Box 218, Folder 8)
  - Chicago Worker: Chicago Unit of ACWM (M-L), Chicago, IL, 1973; cuid11545 (Box 123, Folder 13, Box Shared Tamiment 050, Folder 12)
  - Political Primer for All Americans: CIO Department of Research and Education, Washington, DC, circa 1940s; cuid11546 (Box 101, Folder 27)
  - Liberty Bulletin: Citizens Committee for Constitutional Liberties, New York, NY, 1963; cuid11547 (Box 101, Folder 28)
  - Voices for Liberty: Stop McCarranism! ... Today's McCarthyism: Citizens Committee for Constitutional Liberties, New York, NY, 1963; cuid11548 (Box 101, Folder 29)
  - Student Alcove: Citty College Branch of the Y.C.L, New York, NY, 1936; cuid11549 (Box 101, Folder 30)